Śrīla Gurudev said to me once, and it’s forever ringing in my ears,
Gurudev 对我说的那番话至今仍如铃音洗耳
and with him, sitting on his veranda in Calcutta,
那是在加尔各答，他坐在阳台上
and beneath the framed śloka of Śikṣāṣṭakam of Mahāprabhu:
头顶上镶嵌的是柴坦亚·玛哈帕布的《八训规》
tṛṇād api sunīchena taror iva sahiṣṇunā amāninā mānadena kīrtanīyaḥ sadā hariḥ
tṛṇād api sunīchena taror iva sahiṣṇunā amāninā mānadena kīrtanīyaḥ sadā hariḥ
[“My Religion Is Finding Fault Within Myself”]
我的信仰是反躬自省
So many times he invoked the substance of this śloka:
他多次引用这句诗文的要旨
humility, being humble—
谦卑，宽容
more humble than a blade of grass, more tolerant than a tree,
比小草还要谦卑，比树还要宽容
and giving honor to others without expecting any honor in return.
给予他人荣耀，不祈求回报
And on this particular occasion he said,
在这种情境下他说，
“My religion is finding fault with myself.”
"我的信仰是反躬自省”
“My religion is finding fault with myself.”
“反躬自省”
This is the path to self‒improvement.
这是自我成长的途径
By looking outward into the environment,
凡事向外看
casting blame on the environment or other people,
抱怨环境和其他人
the actors within that environment, circumstances.
把责任归于周遭的一切
All of these excuses that we can make
为自己不正当的行为
for adopting something less than proper behavior.
制造诸多借口
The excuses that we can make for not practicing Vaiṣṇava religion.
文过饰非不去练习外士纳瓦宗
Which Gurudev summed up in that “My religion is finding fault from myself”,
Gurudev将玛哈帕布的训示
and alluding to what is expressed by Mahāprabhu.
总结为“反躬自省”这一准则
And sometimes Śrīla Gurudev would say on the “amāninā mānadena” aspect,
有时，Gurudev还会讲到“amāninā mānadena”的一面
meaning offering respect to others without expecting any in return.
意思是去尊敬对方，不要期待对方回报同样的尊敬
He said, even those who are not worthy of respect,
他还说，即使是那些不值得被尊敬的
or, we could say, who are apparently not worthy of respect.
或者显而易见，没有任何被尊重的价值
Just as it’s easy to be tolerant, when things are tolerable,
就像，我们总是很容易宽容那些易被谅解的事
and it’s easy to be humble in certain circumstances.
在特定的环境中也容易谦卑
So it’s easy to give honor to those who are worthy of honor,
所以，给予那些值得被荣耀的人以荣耀并不是难事
but it’s difficult to practice humility, when our ego is being crushed.
但是，当"小我"受到挫折或者领受侮辱和怠慢
Or if we feel we are being insulted or not recognized.
要练习谦卑就会非常困难
And, the ‘taror iva sahiṣṇunā’— even more tolerant than a tree.
‘taror iva sahiṣṇunā’— 比树还要宽容
Śrīla Guru Mahārāj said that the tree … Someone is cutting down a tree,
Śrīla Guru Mahārāj 说树的宽容，当有人砍掉一棵树
and they are sawing a tree or chopping it down,
人砍伐树的同时
and while they are doing that the tree is providing shade to them.
树还在为他们遮凉
That sort of conception of toleration is being invoked.
当遭遇打击、伤害和不公
That in the midst of being assaulted, attacked, dealt with unfairly,
树的宽容品性便应受到推举
whatever the case might be, the heading might be,
无论发生什么，
still offering shade, shelter.
仍然提供庇护
Like we see sometimes children on the lap of the mother,
就像有时我们看到幼童站在母亲的大腿上
they’re kicking the mother or they are doing things
踢打、玩耍
that if you were older it would be objectionable.
这些长大后不可以做的事情
But they are being tolerated because of love and affection.
但亲情使这些冒犯获得长辈的原谅
And, like what did Gurudev compare it to also?
Gurudev还 举了哪些例子？
He said, “Stool being passed.”
他说，“还有拉屎”
Sometimes they are passing stool on the parent.
有时，婴儿在父母怀里大便
That is not a case for getting rid of the child.
你不能因此就把孩子扔了
[Laughing] He said so,
他就是这么说的
but he used this in the context of the guru and the disciple.
在这里用来比喻Guru和门徒的关系
Devotee will think, “Uh, Kṛṣṇa is in the background,
奉爱者会想，Krishna是一切原因的原因
for some reason He is letting me hear something
他让我听到一些声音，看到一些事情
I am not here to correct others, I’m here to correct myself.
我的存在不是为了纠正别人，而是修正自身
And Gurudev said himself once too, “I am thinking,
Gurudev也说，“我认为
if someone is doing wrong, but they are sincere,
如果有人犯了错，但他们很虔诚
then I am thinking that they’re getting inspiration
那我觉得
So he is delaying correcting them. Thinking they are a sincere person,
因此，他不会马上指出他们的过错，知道他们很虔诚
they’re hearing the voice chaitya-guru within their conscience—
他们会倾听到内在古茹（chaitya-guru）良知的教诲
chaitya-guru by extensions and getting the inspiration for
chaitya-guru会激励他们
inner correction.
去修正自我
So, again, my religion— finding fault with myself.
再次阐明，我的信仰是发现自己的过错
That we can do.
这是我们能做到的
Guru Mahārāj said sometimes
Guru Mahārāj有时会引用
quoting the observations of another men,
他人对《薄伽梵歌》的评论
summarizing saying:
总的来说，《薄伽梵歌》想要告诉我们什么？
“Don’t quarrel with the environment, correct yourself, heal thyself.”
别埋怨环境，纠正自己，疗愈自身
So, that’s our position, but what we find intolerable
这是我们应有的姿态，但令我们无法忍受的
is the blasphemy of other devotees. Not ourselves.
往往不是对自己，而是对其他奉爱者的亵渎
That we can tolerate and think it is deserved.
我们能宽恕他人对我们的冒犯，知道自己罪有应得
But of other devotees, Kṛṣṇa; that is the first offense to the Holy Name.
但是冒犯其他奉爱者，这是对奎师那圣名的第一个冒犯
The very first.
排在最前面的就是冒犯奎师那的奉爱者
Kṛṣṇa won’t tolerate that, and so we don’t tolerate that either.
奎师那不会原谅这样的人，我们也不会
If we can’t do anything about it— we withdraw from the situation.
如果遇到这种事情我们无能无力，那么尽量回避
As Saraswatī Ṭhākur said in Rādhā Kuṇḍa,
有一次，Saraswatī Ṭhākur 在 Rādhā Kuṇḍa说
“If I was just here doing my own bhajan,
“如果我恰好在念诵我的巴赞
and someone said something unfortunate,
一些人在旁边说了些冒失的话
I would just withdraw from there, and I wouldn’t make an issue about it.
我会走开，而不会去挑起事端
But I am here in the role as an Acharya, so I have to.”
但我现在作为一个阿查亚的角色，那我有义务去指正他。”
And actually, when Gurudev told me this,
但实际上，当Gurudev和我说这些的时候
it was … there was someone I couldn’t tolerate.
有个人，我是没办法宽容的
They were offending some other dear devotees of Gurudev.
那个人冒犯了Gurudev 亲密的奉爱者
But Avadhūt Mahārāj and Gurudev were tolerating.
但是Avadhūt Mahārāj 和 Gurudev 宽恕他
So I thought there’s something wrong with me,
所以，我觉得那大概是我错了
so I am going to try and adjust myself.
我试着调整自己
Because I’ve got Gurudev and Avadhūt Mahārāj,
因为，我看到Avadhūt Mahārāj 和 Gurudev很宽容
and they are tolerating, but I can’t tolerate,
而我却做不到
so I’m going to adjust and be like them.
所以我尽力调整自己，像他们那样
So I met with this person and readjusted myself,
调整自己后，我再见到那个人
and I was very proud, and happy of myself,
我非常为自己骄傲和高兴
and I couldn’t wait, and when Gurudev came in,
简直等不及见到Gurudev走进来
and I’m so proud, like a peacock,
我像一只骄傲的孔雀
and then I said, “Mahārāj”, and he said, “Yeah?”
对Gurudev 说，“Maharaj ” 。他说，“嗯？”
I said, “Now I am also seeing that person like you and Avadhūt Mahārāj,
“我现在也能跟你还有 Avadhūt Mahārāj一样看待那个人了
the way you are seeing, I am also seeing like that,
你看待他的视角，我也试着同样去看
I’ve changed my position.”
我改变了自己。”
Like, aren’t I a good boy?
怎么样？我很不错吧？
And Gurudev looked at me, and he goes, “I can never say that.”
Gurudev 看着我，“我可没办法那样讲。”
And I’m like, what? I thought that …
于是我想，我以为...
And that’s when he said, “Finding fault with Vaiṣṇavas …”
这时他说，“挑剔外士纳瓦的错误
and he went through the whole list “… this is intolerable!”
那是无法容忍的。
And he said, “My religion is finding fault with myself,
我的信念是，找自己的错，反躬自省
not casting blame on others, the environment …”
而不是怪罪他人或环境。”
That’s why, ultimately, who are we trying to please?
最终，我们是要取悦谁？
And this is the part that is easy to say, but the bitter pill to swallow.
Krishna和他的奉爱者
We’re trying to please Kṛṣṇa and His devotees.
知易行难
And the ultimate devotee, Rādhārāṇī, says,
作为Krishna的终极奉爱者，Rādhārāṇī说
“If pleasing them involves Me being unhappy on any level,
如果取悦他们使我自己不开心，也没关系
So that’ll be our consideration: sādhu, sāstra, guru, Vaiṣṇav.
我们考虑的是：sādhu, sāstra, guru, Vaiṣṇav（圣人、圣典、古茹、外士纳瓦）
What is ‘them’?
意味着？
vaiṣḥnavī pratiṣṭhā, tāte koro niṣṭhā [Vaiṣḥnava Ke?]
vaiṣḥnavī pratiṣṭhā, tāte koro niṣṭhā
What makes them happy?
怎样才能让他们开心？
Not an egocentric way of viewing everything,
不以自我为中心的看待事物
but theocentric, guru‒centric.
将Guru放在中心
Hare Kṛṣṇa.
哈瑞 奎师那